Guide to the Alva Carmichael Smith papers, 1840-1969 RL.11830
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Alva Carmichael Smith papers
1840-1969
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Smith, Alva Carmichael, 1865-1965
RL.11830
4225 items
Alva Carmichael Smith, businessman, managed the Southern Coal Company at Columbus, Georgia, from about 1911 until the early 1930s. He was active in politics in Columbus, where, in 1941, he had been a member of the local executive committee of the Democratic Party for 22 years.The bulk of the collection includes correspondence (1913-1933), relating to Smith's position as manager of the Southern Coal Company, dealing with miners and shippers in Alabama, Kentucky, and Tennessee, and customers in Alabama and Georgia. Includes material on his membership in the local Kiwanis and Masonic organizations.
Biographical / Historical
Alva Carmichael Smith, businessman, managed the Southern Coal Company at Columbus, Georgia, from about 1911 until the early 1930s. He was active in politics in Columbus, where, in 1941, he had been a member of the local executive committee of the Democratic Party for 22 years. In 1942 he was elected a member of the executive committee for the state. Earlier he had been a delegate to several state political conventions (1906, 1912). He was also active in fraternal organizations - the Freemasons, Knights of Pythias, and Kiwanis, and he was a leader in the Historical Society of Columbus from its inception in 1915. His brother, Henry Clifford Smith, was mayor of Columbus during the 1930s.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Alva Carmichael Smith papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1972.
Collection Overview
Chiefly correspondence (1913-1933), relating to Smith's position as manager of the Southern Coal Company, dealing with miners and shippers in Alabama, Kentucky, and Tennessee, and customers in Alabama and Georgia. Includes material on his membership in the local Kiwanis and Masonic organizations.
Industries -- Alabama; Coal trade -- Southern States.; Industries -- Georgia; Industries -- Kentucky; Men -- Southern States -- Societies and clubs; Industries -- Tennessee; Labor unions -- Southern States; Freemasons. -- Georgia.; Southern Coal Company
- Correspondence, 1898-1943
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence consists of both incoming and outgoing letters that, although numerous, are not a complete file. These business letters date between 1913 and 1933, and are relatively abundant for 1917, 1919-1924, 1926, 1928, and 1930-1932. Since Smith was a middleman, his correspondence reveals aspects of the problems, not only of wholesalers, but also of the miners and shippers of coal and, on the other side, the consumers. The business began about 1911. In 1919 it handled 185 cars of coal between Januarary and September. Coal was purchased directly from the mines for spot cash. Letters about the nature and history of the business include those of: Sept. 20, 1919: April 9, 14, 1920; Feb. 27, 1922; and April 15, 1926.
  The correspondence usually concerns routine matters of purchasing, pricing, selling, and shipping. However, problems of the coal trade were discussed or mentioned with some frequency. Strikes were major or minor difficulties in 1917, 1919-1920, 1922 (see also May 2,1933), 1924, and 1927. The effects of the strikes were the usual topics, but occasionally labor-management problems (as on March 20,1922) and labor union activity were noted. One small mine near Birmingham tried to enhance its competitiveness and labor relations by means of profit-sharing (letter of March 2, 1923). Shortages of railroad cars were serious in 1917and 1919-1920. Early in the latter year the car supply was described as "the worst in Alabama history" and later as "the worst in the history of the coal business" (Oct. 15).
  Wartime requirements and postwar readjustments were occasionally noted. The influenza epidemic also affected the labor force in 1920. Economic distress was mentioned during the Great Depression, especially in 1932. There are a few communications from management associations: the Southeastern Coal Merchants Association (March 20, 23, 24, 1922), and the Southern Appalachian Coal Operators' Association (May 2, 1923).
  Some letters are addressed to Smith's sisters, Mary Elizabeth and Dovie.
  - Correspondence, 1898-1919 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1922 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1924 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1930 March (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1930 April-1933 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1969 (Box 7)
- Financial and Legal Materials, 1916-1943
  Includes legal and financial papers and two volumes: a cashbook (1917-1918) and an order book (1921-1922).
  - Financial papers, 1916-1943 (Box 7)
  - Legal and miscellaneous papers, 1905-1942 (Box 7)
  - Volumes (Box 7)
- Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 7)
- Printed Materials, 1840-1943
  Includes information about the coal trade as well as numerous advertisements from mines and dealers.
  - Printed materials, 1840-1922 (Box 7)
  - Printed materials, 1923-1943 and undated (Box 8)